<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plant breeding | Thiago Oliveira</title>
    <link>https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/tag/plant-breeding/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/tag/plant-breeding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Plant breeding</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Thiago Oliviera</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/media/icon_hucac388deec264b13c6395804f04d3e9e_484996_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Plant breeding</title>
      <link>https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/tag/plant-breeding/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of non-additive genetic variance in breeding programmes</title>
      <link>https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/project/non-additive/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/project/non-additive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
This seeding project aims to build a proof of concept for extending our recently developed framework for temporal and genomic analysis of additive genetic variance in breeding programmes to non-additive genetic variance. The primary purpose of this extension is to quantify the magnitude of non-additive genetic variance and relatedy to quantify the contribution of inbreeding depression and heterosis to genetic gain in breeding programmes.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical models applied to quantitative genetics and genomics of plant breeding</title>
      <link>https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/project/genetic-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://prof-thiagooliveira.netlify.com/project/genetic-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Plant breeding programmes are a complex network of a multitude of operations and decisions. Quantifying the drives of genetic change in such programmes is challenging. Traditionally we measure the genetic change with a phenotypic or genetic trend, but these measures only change the overall genetic mean. To understand the genetic change more comprehensively, we also need to measure the change in genetic variance and drives of mean and variance changes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
To quantify the drives of genetic change in mean we can i) partition breeding values into parent average and Mendelian sampling terms, ii) allocate the terms to analyst-defined &#34;paths&#34; (specific individuals or groups of individuals), and iii) summarise the path specific terms to quantify path contributions to the overall genetic trend in mean. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have used the partitioning method in several cases with profound results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt; To estimate the contribution of different cattle breeding programmes globally and in particular countries; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To estimate the contribution of national selection and import in cattle; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To evaluate national selection and import in pig breeds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
This project aims to apply the partitioning method to plant breeding programmes and to expand its versatility. Specifically, we are aiming to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt; Utilise genomic information to identify which genome regions drive genetic change and which sources contribute to favourable alleles in these genome regions &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyse changes in genetic variance in addition to the genetic mean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Account for uncertainty in genetic trends and their partitions, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop an R package&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
